{
  "phrases": [
    {
      "id": "card_n_p1",
      "front": "昔 妖狐ありけり。",
      "back": "Long ago, there was a demonic fox.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w14",
        "card_n_w15",
        "card_n_w16"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p2",
      "front": "そのきつね 九つの尾あり。",
      "back": "That fox had nine tails.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w17",
        "card_n_w18",
        "card_n_w19"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p3",
      "front": "その尾 一度振らば山崩れ 津波立つ。",
      "back": "If that tail was swung even once, mountains would crumble and tsunamis would rise.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w19",
        "card_n_w20",
        "card_n_w21",
        "card_n_w22",
        "card_n_w23",
        "card_n_w24"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p4",
      "front": "これに困じて人ども",
      "back": "Troubled by this, the people...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w25",
        "card_n_w26"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p5",
      "front": "忍のやからを集めけり。",
      "back": "...gathered the ninja clans.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w27",
        "card_n_w28",
        "card_n_w29"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p6",
      "front": "四代目が来るまで足止めをかけろ！",
      "back": "Hold them off until the Fourth Hokage arrives!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w30",
        "card_n_w31",
        "card_n_w32"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p7",
      "front": "これ以上一歩も里に近づけるな！",
      "back": "Don't let it get one step closer to the village!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w33",
        "card_n_w34",
        "card_n_w35",
        "card_n_w36"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p8",
      "front": "僅か１人が忍の者",
      "back": "Only one ninja...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w37",
        "card_n_w27",
        "card_n_w38"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p9",
      "front": "生死を懸けこれを封印せしめるが",
      "back": "...risked his life and death to seal it, but...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w39",
        "card_n_w40",
        "card_n_w41",
        "card_n_w42"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p10",
      "front": "その者 死にけり。",
      "back": "That person died.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w38",
        "card_n_w43"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p11",
      "front": "その忍の者 名を",
      "back": "The name of that ninja...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w27",
        "card_n_w38"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p12",
      "front": "四代目 火影と申す。",
      "back": "...is called the Fourth Hokage.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w30",
        "card_n_w44",
        "card_n_w45"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p13",
      "front": "ヒャ～ッハッハッハ…！",
      "back": "Hya-hahahaha...!",
      "related_ids": [],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p46",
      "front": "ヘッヘッヘ～！こら ナルト！",
      "back": "Heh heh heh~! Hey! Naruto!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w57",
        "card_n_w58"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p47",
      "front": "何ちゅう罰当たりなことをしたんだ！",
      "back": "What kind of sacrilegious thing did you do?!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w59",
        "card_n_w60",
        "card_n_w61"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p48",
      "front": "きょうという きょうは絶対許さんぞ！",
      "back": "Today of all days, I absolutely won't forgive you!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w62",
        "card_n_w63",
        "card_n_w64"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p49",
      "front": "ハ～ッハッハッハッ！うっせぇんだってばよ！",
      "back": "Hahaha! Shut up, believe it!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w65",
        "card_n_w66"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p50",
      "front": "お前らさ お前らさあ～んなマネできねえだろ？",
      "back": "Hey, you guys, you guys can't pull off a stunt like that, right?",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w67",
        "card_n_w68",
        "card_n_w69"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p51",
      "front": "だけど俺にはできる俺は すごいんだってばよ！",
      "back": "But I can do it! I'm amazing, believe it!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w70",
        "card_n_w71",
        "card_n_w72",
        "card_n_w66"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p52",
      "front": "大変です 三代目！火影様！",
      "back": "It's terrible, Third Hokage! Lord Hokage!",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w73",
        "card_n_w74",
        "card_n_w75"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p53",
      "front": "何じゃ？ またナルトのヤツが",
      "back": "What is it? Did that Naruto guy again...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w76",
        "card_n_w77"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p54",
      "front": "何か しでかしでもしたか？",
      "back": "...do something mischievous?",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w78"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p55",
      "front": "はい 歴代火影様たちの顔岩に…｡",
      "back": "Yes, on the faces carved into the rock of the previous Hokages...",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w79",
        "card_n_w75",
        "card_n_w80"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_p56",
      "front": "恐れ多くも落書きを…｡",
      "back": "...they dared to graffiti them.",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_w81",
        "card_n_w82"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "phrase"
    }
  ],
  "words": [
    {
      "id": "card_n_w14",
      "front": "昔",
      "front_furigana": "むかし",
      "front_romaji": "mukashi",
      "back": "Long ago, the past",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p1"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w15",
      "front": "妖狐",
      "front_furigana": "ようこ",
      "front_romaji": "yōko",
      "back": "Demonic fox, kitsune",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p1"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w16",
      "front": "ありけり",
      "front_furigana": "ありけり",
      "front_romaji": "arikeru",
      "back": "(Classical) There was/were",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p1"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w17",
      "front": "きつね",
      "front_furigana": "きつね",
      "front_romaji": "kitsune",
      "back": "Fox",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p2"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w18",
      "front": "九つ",
      "front_furigana": "ここのつ",
      "front_romaji": "kokonotsu",
      "back": "Nine (things)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p2"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w19",
      "front": "尾",
      "front_furigana": "お",
      "front_romaji": "o",
      "back": "Tail",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p2",
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w20",
      "front": "一度",
      "front_furigana": "いちど",
      "front_romaji": "ichido",
      "back": "Once, one time",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w21",
      "front": "振らば",
      "front_furigana": "ふらば",
      "front_romaji": "furaba",
      "back": "(Classical conditional) If it swings/is swung",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w22",
      "front": "山崩れ",
      "front_furigana": "やまくずれ",
      "front_romaji": "yamakuzure",
      "back": "Landslide, mountain collapse",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w23",
      "front": "津波",
      "front_furigana": "つなみ",
      "front_romaji": "tsunami",
      "back": "Tsunami, tidal wave",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w24",
      "front": "立つ",
      "front_furigana": "たつ",
      "front_romaji": "tatsu",
      "back": "To rise, to stand up, to occur",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p3"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w25",
      "front": "困じる",
      "front_furigana": "こんじる",
      "front_romaji": "konjiru",
      "back": "To be troubled, to be distressed",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p4"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w26",
      "front": "人ども",
      "front_furigana": "ひとども",
      "front_romaji": "hitodomo",
      "back": "People (plural)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p4"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w27",
      "front": "忍",
      "front_furigana": "しのび",
      "front_romaji": "shinobi",
      "back": "Ninja",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p5",
        "card_n_p8",
        "card_n_p11"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w28",
      "front": "やから",
      "front_furigana": "やから",
      "front_romaji": "yakara",
      "back": "Clan, family, group",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p5"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w29",
      "front": "集める",
      "front_furigana": "あつめる",
      "front_romaji": "atsumeru",
      "back": "To gather, to collect",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p5"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w30",
      "front": "四代目",
      "front_furigana": "よんだいめ",
      "front_romaji": "yondaime",
      "back": "The Fourth (generation/successor)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p6",
        "card_n_p12"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w31",
      "front": "来る",
      "front_furigana": "くる",
      "front_romaji": "kuru",
      "back": "To come, to arrive",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p6"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w32",
      "front": "足止めをかける",
      "front_furigana": "あしどめをかける",
      "front_romaji": "ashidome o kakeru",
      "back": "To hold back, to detain, to stall",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p6"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w33",
      "front": "これ以上",
      "front_furigana": "これいじょう",
      "front_romaji": "kore ijō",
      "back": "Any more than this, beyond this",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p7"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w34",
      "front": "一歩",
      "front_furigana": "いっぽ",
      "front_romaji": "ippo",
      "back": "One step",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p7"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w35",
      "front": "里",
      "front_furigana": "さと",
      "front_romaji": "sato",
      "back": "Village, hometown",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p7"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w36",
      "front": "近づける",
      "front_furigana": "ちかづける",
      "front_romaji": "chikazukeru",
      "back": "To bring closer, to let approach",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p7"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w37",
      "front": "僅か",
      "front_furigana": "わずか",
      "front_romaji": "wazuka",
      "back": "Only a little, slight, few",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p8"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w38",
      "front": "者",
      "front_furigana": "もの",
      "front_romaji": "mono",
      "back": "Person, individual",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p8",
        "card_n_p10",
        "card_n_p11"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w39",
      "front": "生死",
      "front_furigana": "せいし",
      "front_romaji": "seishi",
      "back": "Life and death",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p9"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w40",
      "front": "懸ける",
      "front_furigana": "かける",
      "front_romaji": "kakeru",
      "back": "To risk, to bet",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p9"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w41",
      "front": "封印",
      "front_furigana": "ふういん",
      "front_romaji": "fūin",
      "back": "Seal, sealing",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p9"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w42",
      "front": "せしめる",
      "front_furigana": "せしめる",
      "front_romaji": "seshimeru",
      "back": "(Classical/Formal) To cause to do, to manage to do",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p9"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w43",
      "front": "死ぬ",
      "front_furigana": "しぬ",
      "front_romaji": "shinu",
      "back": "To die",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p10"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w44",
      "front": "火影",
      "front_furigana": "ほかげ",
      "front_romaji": "Hokage",
      "back": "Hokage (Fire Shadow, village leader title)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p12"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w45",
      "front": "申す",
      "front_furigana": "もうす",
      "front_romaji": "mōsu",
      "back": "To say, to be called (humble/formal)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p12"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w57",
      "front": "こら",
      "front_furigana": "こら",
      "front_romaji": "kora",
      "back": "Hey! / Stop it! (used to scold)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p46"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w58",
      "front": "ナルト",
      "front_furigana": "なると",
      "front_romaji": "Naruto",
      "back": "Naruto (Character name)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p46"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w59",
      "front": "何ちゅう",
      "front_furigana": "なんちゅう",
      "front_romaji": "nanchuu",
      "back": "What kind of (colloquial contraction of 何という)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p47"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w60",
      "front": "罰当たり",
      "front_furigana": "ばちあたり",
      "front_romaji": "bachi atari",
      "back": "Sacrilegious; deserving of divine punishment",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p47"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w61",
      "front": "した",
      "front_furigana": "した",
      "front_romaji": "shita",
      "back": "Did (past tense of する)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p47"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w62",
      "front": "きょう",
      "front_furigana": "きょう",
      "front_romaji": "kyou",
      "back": "Today",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p48"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w63",
      "front": "絶対",
      "front_furigana": "ぜったい",
      "front_romaji": "zettai",
      "back": "Absolutely; definitely",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p48"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w64",
      "front": "許さん",
      "front_furigana": "ゆるさん",
      "front_romaji": "yurusan",
      "back": "Won't forgive (colloquial/masculine negative form of 許す)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p48"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w65",
      "front": "うっせぇ",
      "front_furigana": "うっせぇ",
      "front_romaji": "ussee",
      "back": "Shut up! (Slang/contraction of うるさい)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p49"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w66",
      "front": "だってばよ",
      "front_furigana": "だってばよ",
      "front_romaji": "dattebayo",
      "back": "Believe it! (Naruto's catchphrase/sentence ender)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p49",
        "card_n_p51"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w67",
      "front": "お前ら",
      "front_furigana": "おまえら",
      "front_romaji": "omaera",
      "back": "You guys (plural, informal/rude)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p50"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w68",
      "front": "マネ",
      "front_furigana": "まね",
      "front_romaji": "mane",
      "back": "Imitation; stunt; trick",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p50"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w69",
      "front": "できねえ",
      "front_furigana": "できねえ",
      "front_romaji": "dekinee",
      "back": "Cannot do (Slang/contraction of できない)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p50"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w70",
      "front": "だけど",
      "front_furigana": "だけど",
      "front_romaji": "dakedo",
      "back": "But; however",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p51"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w71",
      "front": "俺",
      "front_furigana": "おれ",
      "front_romaji": "ore",
      "back": "I (masculine, informal)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p51"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w72",
      "front": "すごい",
      "front_furigana": "すごい",
      "front_romaji": "sugoi",
      "back": "Amazing; incredible",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p51"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w73",
      "front": "大変",
      "front_furigana": "たいへん",
      "front_romaji": "taihen",
      "back": "Terrible; serious; difficult",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p52"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w74",
      "front": "三代目",
      "front_furigana": "さんだいめ",
      "front_romaji": "sandaime",
      "back": "Third generation/Third",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p52"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w75",
      "front": "火影様",
      "front_furigana": "ほかげさま",
      "front_romaji": "hokage sama",
      "back": "Lord Hokage",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p52",
        "card_n_p55"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w76",
      "front": "何じゃ",
      "front_furigana": "なんじゃ",
      "front_romaji": "nan ja",
      "back": "What is it? (colloquial/old-fashioned)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p53"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w77",
      "front": "ヤツ",
      "front_furigana": "やつ",
      "front_romaji": "yatsu",
      "back": "Guy; fellow (often derogatory or familiar)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p53"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w78",
      "front": "しでかし",
      "front_furigana": "しでかし",
      "front_romaji": "shidekashi",
      "back": "Mischief; blunder (noun form of しでかす)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p54"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w79",
      "front": "歴代",
      "front_furigana": "れきだい",
      "front_romaji": "rekidai",
      "back": "Successive generations; previous",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p55"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w80",
      "front": "顔岩",
      "front_furigana": "かお・いわ",
      "front_romaji": "kao iwa",
      "back": "Face rock (The carved faces of the Hokages)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p55"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w81",
      "front": "恐れ多くも",
      "front_furigana": "おそれおおくも",
      "front_romaji": "osore ooku mo",
      "back": "Daringly; presumptuously (often used sarcastically or in formal reports of transgression)",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p56"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    },
    {
      "id": "card_n_w82",
      "front": "落書き",
      "front_furigana": "らくがき",
      "front_romaji": "rakugaki",
      "back": "Graffiti; scribble",
      "related_ids": [
        "card_n_p56"
      ],
      "deck_id": "1",
      "type": "word"
    }
  ]
}